Finding Aid for Detroit Observatory (University of Michigan) records, 1860-2004
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Historical 1860-2004, 14 linear feet
  - Audiovisual Materials
    - Photographs
      - Observatories and Scientific Instruments (other)
        - Cerra Tololo Interamerican Observatory (near Santiago, Chile) (Box 17)
          (accession no. 143)
        - Hopkins Observatory, Williams College, Williamstown, MA (Box 17)
          (accession nos. 233-234)
        - Kitt Peak in Arizona? (Box 17)
          (accession no. 276)
        - Maine? Equipment for Solar Eclipse Viewing (Box 17)
          (accession nos. 230, 300-301)
        - McMath-Hulbert Observatory
          - (accession no. 331) (Box 17)
          - (accession no. 298) (Box 17)
        - Pyrenees (Box 17)
          (accession no. 263)
        - Radio Telescope (Box 17)
          (accession no. 341)
        - Unidentified Observatories
          - Jane Berry Collection Photographs (Box 17)
            (accession nos. 235-252, 255)
          - Telescope Inside Dome (Box 17)
            (accession no. 254)
          - Two Men Seated Inside Observatory (Box 17)
            (accession no. 253)
          - Young Man Observing Through Large Telescope Inside Dome (Box 17)
            (accession no. 299)
      - People
        - Madeline McMath (Box 17)
          (accession no. 140)
        - Robert McMath (Box 17)
          (accession nos. 332, 335, 338)
        - Portrait of a woman (Box 17)
          (accession no. 138)
        - Portrait of a young girl (Box 17)
          (found behind accession no. 138)
        - Two men in observatory (Box 17)
        - Two women and one girl (Box 17)
          (accession no. 231)
        - Woman looking at lantern slides (Box 17)
          (accession no. 339)
    - Lantern Slides
      - Planets and sunspots and other astronomy observation photographs, 22 slides (Box 17)
        (accession no. 172)
      - Observatory equipment and various Observatory buildings, 16 slides (Box 17)
        (accession no. 149)
      - Detroit Observatory building 1854 (Box 17)
        (accession no. 148)
    - Negatives
      [See Also: Artifact Photographs in boxes 1 & 2]
      - Artifacts (Box 17)
      - Astronomical instruments August 2, 1996 (Box 17)
      - Restoration 1996-1999 Rolls 1-137, 5 folders (Box 17)
    - Etchings
      - Etchings of Detroit Observatory by Cropsey & Leggett (set of 8) (Box 17)
        (accession no. 130)
      - Etching of Detroit Observatory by Cropsey & Leggett (Box 17)
        (accession no. 182)
    - Sunspot Maps
      - Mount Wilson sunspot maps, positive film 1925-1941, 1949-1958, 6 rolls (Box 18)
      - Mount Wilson & Polomar Observatory, magnetic observations of sunspots 1959-1961, 2 rolls (Box 18)
      - Polarity Drawings 1958 (Box 18)
    - Slides
      - Unidentified slides of graphs and data, from McMath-Hulbert Observatory?, 35 slides approximate (Box 18)
    - Glass lantern slides, 11 slides (Box 27)
      (BHL accession 1/29/2008)
      - Halley's Comet
        - May 5, 1910
        - May 8, 1910
        - May 9, 1910
        - May 25, 1910
        - May 26, 1910, 2 slides
        - May 27, 1910
      - Moon taken with 12" refractor
        - May 22, 1920
        - May 28, 1920
        - December 20, 1920
      - Praesepe-the Beehive, taken with 3" finder undated
    - Slides
      (Detroit Observatory Collection accession #320, transferred from Observatory location to Bentley Library, largely undated. Description taken from Detroit Observatory Object database)
      - Planets-Configs Kepler areas
      - Scenic moon star trails
      - Moon
      - Earth
      - Mercury
      - Venus
      - Mars
      - Jupiter
      - Saturn
      - Comets
      - Milky way
      - Radio sources
      - Galaxies-radio resolution
      - Types of galaxies
      - Clusters of galaxies
      - SB 5688
      - CD-29*13998
      - MHa36211
      - 1H10M-60*.9
      - 16H15M-52*
      - 7 cyg neb
      - Nebulae ngc#
      - Unsorted slides
      - 1.3m spectra
      - Small box "Mirrors, prism grating, slits, filters"
    - Spectrograph glass plate circa 1918
      (BHL accession 9/19/2006)
    - Slides, Detroit Observatory Collection accession #147, 4 boxes
      (transferred from Observatory location to Bentley Library August 2009. Description taken from Detroit Observatory Object database)
      - Slide Box 1 circa 1915-1970 (Box 28)
        - Sunspots
        - Largest spots
        - Isophotes
        - E-bombs
        - Flares
        - Lya BaK-white sun
        - Disc sp'grams
        - Solar terr
        - Spot cycles
        - Sodium D2
        - Corona
        - Solar spectrum
        - 4985 Fe
        - Prominence spectra
        - Prominences
        - 1972 Jul 10 Prim Pt. PE Island Dennis Skelton
        - 1970 Mar 07 Sandbridge VA
        - Eclipse diagrams
        - Eclipse exps
        - Ca K center
        - Magnetic splitting
        - Sodium D1
        - Unknown
      - Slide Box 2 circa 1929-1987 (Box 28)
        - McDonald Observatory
        - Mt. Lemmon Observatory
        - Mt. Stropilo Goode
        - Mt. Wo site
        - Mt. Wo 1.52m
        - Mt. Wo 2.54m
        - Palomar 1.22m
        - Perkins Observatory OWU
        - Pulkovo cccp
        - Purple Mt Obs. Nanking China
        - Raisin River Pettit
        - Ritter Observatory, University of Toledo
        - USNO
        - USNO large refractor 0 Van Vleck Observatory Wesleyan University
        - Yale Radio Observatory
        - Yerkes 40 inch
        - Stroke Ruling engine
        - JW Fecker shop telescopes,1929
        - Constellations
        - Constellation
        - Atmosphere sunrise sunset night lights
        - WWJTV 304.8 m tower above cloud
        - Hydraulic drive
        - The Eye
        - Misc Tololo Serena
      - Slide Box 3 circa 1908-1983 (Box 29)
        - Astronomers
        - Cranbrook Institute of Science
        - Kepler
        - University of Michigan Directors history
        - Detroit Observatory exteriors including views of Director's residence
        - Walker Meridian circle
        - Fitz telescope 12 1/4 inch
        - University of Michigan 37 inch reflector
        - Lamont Hussey Observatory
        - Curtis Telescope Stinchfield
        - Angell Hall Observatory
        - FC McMath Meridian
        - Physics Astronomy Denison Building
        - Peach Mountain
        - UM 1.3 telescope
        - McMath Hulbert Exteriors
        - MCM HO Instrument
        - Radio telescope
        - Albion College Observatory
        - CAO cccp
        - Case WRU 10 in. 1
        - University of Arizona Catalina Observatory
        - Einstein tower Potsdam
        - Haleakala project Michigan
        - Harvard Radio Observatory Texas
        - Haute Provence
        - Institut D'Astrophysique Cointe
        - Isaac Newton telescope
        - KPNO, general
        - KPNO 4m telescope
        - KPNO McMath telescope
        - La Plata Observatory
        - Lick Observatory
        - Lindheimer Dearborn Northwestern
        - Lowell
      - Slide Box 4 plus one folder of slides, unclassified circa 1946-1965 (Box 28)
        - Slides for 196 Halle in London IQST "History and Morphology" HDP & Budapest
        - Time variations in solar activity leningrad paper
        - Eclipse March 7, 1970
        - Unsorted (unsorted also placed in slide sleeves in separate folder)
        - Huntsville; time & space
        - 29.5 day study
        - Spectra
        - Lantern slides related to IQST studies
        - Cosmic ray event behind sun 01/28/1967
        - Slides related to pre and post activity of proton flare 7/7/1966
        - Mcg spectra for capri meeting
        - Slides related to IQST-Madrid, Washington & Philadelphia talks
        - 4 broken slides
    - Audiocassettes
      - WUOM-Detroit Observatory August 28, 1997 (Box 18)
      - Michigan Public Radio Interview, Patricia S. Whitesell August 9, 1999 (Box 18)
      - Oral History, Freeman D. Miller April 30, 1996 (Box 18)
        (accession no. 303)
      - Rededication May 21, 1999 (Box 18)
        (accession no. 356)
    - Reel-to-Reel, 4 reels
      - Placing Dome on McGregor Tower 1940 (Box 18)
        (accession no. 272)
      - Clarkston-swimming; Pete-moon 1928 (Box 18)
        (accession no. 273)
      - 50 foot tower (Box 18)
        (accession no. 274)
      - Leo Goldberg's picture of Portage Lake and Harry Hulbert 1949 (Box 18)
        (accession no. 275)
    - Videotapes (Box 19)
      - View of the Observatory from June 18, 1997-1998, 7 videotapes (Box 19)
      - Historic Films (Box 19)
        (four films transferred to a single videotape)
        - Photos of the Moon, taken in 1928 by Robert McMath using a 4-inch Telescope
        - Construction of 50-foot tower, McMath Observatory 1936
        - Construction of McGregor Tower, McMath Observatory 1940
        - Leo Goldberg, Harvey Holbert and Portage Lake Facility 1949
      - News programs featuring the Observatory
        - Community Television Network May 21, 2000 (Box 19)
        - Channel 4 News, WDIV Detroit (Box 19)
        - FYI (Box 19)
          (Ann Arbor cable program)
      - Surveying Michigan, by Lansing Community College 1991 (Box 19)
    - Digital Media
      - Illustrations for A Creation of His Own, 10 zip disks (Box 19)
      - Museum Methods 406 class 2002, 3 zip disks; 1 optical disks CD-ROMs (Box 19)
      - Unidentified, 5 zip disks (Box 19)
  - Artifacts
    The artifacts subseries consists of several objects that were transferred to the Bentley Historical Library. The artifacts include a gold medal presented to Franz Brünnow in 1848 and two scientific instruments: an anemometer and a spectrograph. Researchers wishing to see other Observatory instruments should visit the Detroit Observatory.
    - Anemometer (Box 20)
      (accession no. 113)
    - Gold Medal Presented to Franz Brünnow in 1848 for his research on De Vico's Comet
      (accession no. 383)
      (stored in vault)
    - Documentation for Sextant Bubble (Box 20)
      (for accession no. 25)
    - Anemometer
      (artifact, stored in Bentley basement stairwell)
    - Spectrograph
      (accession no. 117)
    - Note and Newspaper Fragment Found Under Dome Stairs at Observatory During Restoration 1997-1998 (Box 20)
      (accession nos. 145-146)
    - Files used in Detroit Observatory and other UM Observatories (Box 20)
      (including star charts, record sheets, and personnel list for Astronomy Department)
      (accession no. 285)
    - Notecards
      - Directions (Box 20)
        (accession no. 232)
      - Inventory (Box 20)
        (accession no. 302)
    - Piece of Ribbon from Ribbon Cutting Ceremony from Observatory Rededication May 21, 1999 (Box 20)
    - Unidentified Newspaper (Box 20)
    - Unidentified Recorded Disks, some labeled "code adaptive test" (Box 20)
      (accession nos. 259-262)
- Publications 1863-2001
  The Publications series (1863-2001, 3 linear ft.) includes publications about the Detroit Observatory and its holdings as well as historical publications covering the history of astronomy. (Researchers interested in additional publications on the Detroit Observatory and the history of Astronomy, May also want to consult the following publications, which can be found in the University of Michigan Library.)
  - Contemporary
    - DuRussel, Mark, Thomas Graf, and Nicholas Steneck. Historic Instrument Survey, The University of Michigan. (1988) (Box 20)
    - Carl Rufus Articles, 1 volumes (Box 21)
    - Crawford, Pamela and James Robertson. Detroit Observatory: Architectural Design Project. (Box 21)
    - Frontiers in History: People, Places Ideas: National History Day, 2001 (Box 21)
      [photocopy]
    - Historical Writing on American Science: Perspectives and Prospects (Box 21)
    - Jarrell, Richard A. J. S. Plaskett and the Modern Large Reflecting Telescope. (1999) (Box 21)
    - Jones, Bessie Zaban and Lyle Gifford Boyd. The Harvard College Observatory: the First Four Directorships, 1839-1919. 1971 (Box 21)
    - Kodak plates and film for science and industry. (Box 21)
      (accession no. 284)
    - Sky and Telescope Lunar Map (Box 21)
    - Old West Side Story: Germans in Ann Arbor (Box 21)
      [newspaper article]
  - Historical
    - Becvár, Antonín. Atlas of the Heavens: Atlas Coeli 1950.0, circa 1958 (Box 22)
    - Campbell, William Wallace and Heber Doust Curtis. First Catalogue of Spectroscopic Binaries.. circa 1905 (Box 22)
      (accession no. 211)
    - Chauvenet, William.
      - A Manual of Spherical and Practical Astronomy Embracing the General Problems of..., 5th ed. revised and corrected, Vol. I, circa 1863 (Box 22)
        (accession no. 214)
      - A Treatise on Plane and Spherical Trigonometry. circa 1878 (Box 22)
        (accession no. 194)
    - [Constellation Charts] (Map-case 245)
    - Curtis, Heber Doust.
      - Definitive Determination of the Orbit of Comet 1898 I. circa 1902 (Box 22)
        (accession no. 209)
      - Miscellaneous Papers by Heber D. Curtis (Box 22)
        (accession no. 197)
      - The New McGregor Building and 70-foot Tower Telescope of the McMath-Hulbert Observatory. circa 1940 (Box 22)
        (accession no. 321 and 343)
      - Recent Changes at the Observatory of the D.O. Mills Expedition. (1907) (Box 22)
        (accession no. 199)
      - The System of Castor. circa 1906 (Box 22)
        (accession no. 198)
      - Temperature Control; Spectroscopic Binaries (Box 22)
        (accession no. 196)
    - Hussey, William J. Logarithmic and other Mathematical Tables (5th ed.) (Box 22)
    - Jordan, Wilhelm. Taschenbuch der Praktischen Geometrie. circa 1873 (Box 22)
      (accession no. 216)
    - Keenan, Joseph H. and Frederick G. Keyes. Thermodynamic Properties of Steam: Including Data for the Liquid and Solid Phases. circa 1936 (Box 23)
    - Max Kohl (Firm) Max Kohl: Preisliste no. 12 Physikalische Apparate; Nachtrag I zu Preisliste no. 12 Uber Physikalische Apparateca. circa 1901 (Box 23)
    - McMath, Robert R., Francis C. McMath and Henry S. Hulbert. The McMath-Hulbert Observatory (Box 23)
      (accession no. 322)
    - Michaelson, Albert A. The Velocity of Light., circa 1878 (Box 23)
    - Miller, Freeman D. The Portage Lake Observatory of the University of Michigan. circa 1950 (Box 23)
      (accession no. 323)
    - Moulton, Forest Ray. Introduction to Celestial Mechanics, circa 1935 (Box 23)
    - Price, Edward W. The Essence of Astronomy: Things Every One Should Know About the Sun, Moon, and Stars. circa 1914 (Box 23)
    - Publications of the Astronomical and Astrophysical Society of Michigan. (Box 23)
      (Volumes 1-3)
    - Rossiter, Richard Alfred. Catalogue of Southern Double Stars (1955) (Box 23)
      (accession no. 134)
  - Architectural and Mechanical Drawings
    - Key plan 1988 (Map-case 245)
    - Restoration Drawings
      - 1970s architectural plans with restoration annotations, 3 drawings (Map-case 245)
      - 1975 west wall restoration, 2 drawings (Map-case 245)
      - 1984, 4 drawings (Map-case 245)
      - 1997 restoration: design development submission and project manual for Detroit Observatory Restoration, January 1997, 145 drawings approximate (Map-case 245)
      - Schematic Design Submission November 15, 1997, 1 volumes bound set (Map-case 245)
      - Design Development Submission January 10, 1997, 2 volumes bound sets (Map-case 245)
      - Construction Documents Submission March 7, 1997, 1 volumes bound set (Map-case 245)
      - Bid Documents April 28, 1997, 1 volumes bound set (Map-case 245)
    - Scientific instruments
      - Mounting 52" telescope, Kitt Peak Observatory, 8 drawings (Map-case 245)
        (accession no. 266)
      - Design of 50" telescope for the University of Michigan, including: dimensions for location of telescope in dome, layout of main tube, control cabinet proposal, polar axis layout, 6 drawings (Map-case 245)
        (accession no. 267)
      - Design of 48" telescope. one drawing includes both 48" and 50" telescopes, 13 drawings (Map-case 245)
        (accession no. 268)
      - Proposed Coude Spectrograph for the University of Michigan (Map-case 245)
        (accession no. 269)
      - Parts related to telescopes or telescope use, 4 drawings
        (accession no. 270)
Related Material
Other related Bentley collections include the University of Michigan Observatory record group. The Observatory record group contains material on the Detroit Observatory, including inventories, budgets, personnel, and account books from approximately 1908 to 1948.
Bibliography
Researchers interested in additional publications on the Detroit Observatory and the history of Astronomy, may also want to consult the following publications, which can be found in the University of Michigan Library:
Andre, Charles Louis Francois, Georges Rayet, et Alfred Angot. L'astronomie Pratique et les Observatoires en Europe et en Amerique Depuis le Milieu du XVIIe siecle jusqu'a nos jours, Parts 1-5
The Astronomical Journal, v.5 (1856-1858), v.6 (1859-1861)
A Brief Account of the Lick Observatory of the University of California (1927)
Forbes, George. The Transit of Venus (1874)
A History of the First Half-century of the National Academy of Sciences, 1863-1913 (1913)
Holden, Edward S. Hand-book of the Lick Observatory of the University of California (1888)
Instructions for Observing the Total Solar Eclipse of July 29, 1878 (1878)
The Michigan Technic, Volume 11 (1895)
Observations of the Transit of Venus, December 8-9, 1874. (1880) (part I)
Reports on Observations of the Total Eclipse of the Sun, August 7, 1869 (1870)
Reports on the Observations of the Total Eclipse of the Sun of January 1, 1889 (Contributions from the Lick Observatory). (1889)
Reports on Observations of the Total Solar Eclipse of December 22, 1870 (1871)
Smyth, C. Piazzi. A Poor Man's Photography at the Great Pyramid in the Year 1865... (1870)
Todd, David Peck. The Lick Observatory, Mount Hamilton, California (1885).
Todd, Mabel Loomis. Total Eclipses of the Sun (no. 1) (1894)
United States Naval Observatory. Reports on the Total Solar Eclipses of July 29, 1878 and January 11, 1880 (1880)